# 大家好 今天天氣比較好哦
Hi everyone! The weather is much better today.
# 我搞點金銀花回去吃哦
I'm gonna get some honeysuckles back home.
# 就這 你看
Over there, look!
# 一大片
They're everywhere.
# 我把它割下來
I'm gonna cut them off,
# 通通割下來
cut them all off.
# 哇 好茂盛啊
Wa! It's so bushy here.
# 把這個整片把它割下來
I cut off the whole bunch of it.
# 這個割完之後還會長出來哦 這個藤子
It keeps on growing after cutting them off, I mean the stem.
# 長得很快的
It grows really fast.
# 割一下明年長的更多
Cutting it helps it grow even more next year.
# 哇 好香啊
Wa! It smells so nice!
# 一種那種淡淡的香味
It's sort of like a subtle fragrance.
# 問[SIC]一下這個味道 (註︰"Smell"這個字不合這裡的意境，故避用)
It's a fragrance, which,
# 真的很舒服的
makes you feel really great.
# 我們去另外一個地方搞
Let's move to another place.
# 這個太少啦 就一點點
It's too few here, just a tiny little bit.
# 你看 這裡好多啊 這裡
Look! Here are a lot, here.
# 一片一片的
They're in bunches.
# 早知道我拿兩個籮筐來 一個籮筐裝了多少
I should have come with two buckets. I can't take too much with just one.
# 這個
Here are,
# 那個多
so many.
# 快點走 不怕 我牽你去
C'mon, let's go! I'm holding you hand, so don't be afraid.
# 快點 我牽你去
C'mon! I'm holding your hand.
# 就在那邊 看到沒有那麼漂亮的牛你都不敢去
They're right over there! Can you see them? Why don't you dare to go? The cattle are so pretty.
# 大家刘星辰都坐在牛背上騎牛 (註︰「人家」這譯不到，唯有用另一種說法突出他想表達刘星辰膽子大)
You know what? Liu Xingchen even dares to ride on a cow!
# 真的 不騙你
No kidding. I'm serious.
# 你要你自己去
No, leave me alone.
# 不是騎 看
We're not riding! We just watch.
# 我帶你去喝牛奶 去不去
Let's go to have some milk. Are you going with me?
# 那裡有牛奶的哦
There's milk, you know.
# 去不去
Are you going?
# 韋汝 過來
Come here, Weiru.
# 沒事的 跳下來
No worries! Just jump down the step!
# 我不敢跳
But I dare not.
# 怎麼不敢跳 你多少歲啦 (註︰「啦」有「已經有少了」的意思，不能譯，明示一下)
Why don't you dare? You're not a baby anymore. How old are you?
# 有五歲了
Already five
# 你看 這都是兄弟家的牛哦
Look! These are all my buddy's cattle.
# 這幾條 幾萬塊呀
These several here are worth tens of thousands of RMB.
# 現在牛肉貴
Beef is expensive these days.
# 我再去摘點金銀花 就摘了一點點金銀花
I'll go on with the honeysuckles. I've just picked a tiny little bit.
# 看到這個牛
I come to see the cattle,
# 那麼可愛就過來看一下
as I found that they're so cute.
# 走
Let's go!
# 繼續摘
Back to the honeysuckles
# 好漂亮嗎
Is it pretty?
# 你有這種顏色的花嗎
Do you have any flowers in this colour?
# 這個
This colour?
# 對啊
Yup!
# 這種哦
I mean this one.
# 我也有這種
Yes, I have this one too.
# 這種 我這個比你大
This one, mine is larger than yours.
# 這個好靚哦
It's really beautiful!
# 胡韋汝快點滴 別偷懶哦
Keep picking, Hu Weiru! Don't be a slacker!
# 等下我摘的我不給你哦
You're not gonna get your share if you don't work.
# 你看 這個好靚的哦 這種
Look! This is really beautiful, isn't it?
# 剛好變黃色的
They have just turned yellow.
# 變黃色才好吃
It tastes much better when it has turned yellow,
# 就快謝了 但是沒謝的那一種
the ones which are about to whither, but have not yet withered.
# 你看 摘金銀花的話 這個
Look! When you're picking the honeysuckles,
# 這種還沒開苞的
look for this kind of buds which have not yet blossomed,
# 或者這種白色的或變黃色了都可以摘
or this kind of white ones, or the yellow ones. All are fine.
# 這個就像
It's like,
# 小 小男孩一樣 這個
like a lit, little boy, this one.
# 這種就小男孩
This is a little boy.
# 這種就是青年
And this is a young man.
# 這種就是像我這種 嘖
And this is, just like me, I mean,
# 三十多歲的這種 這種
somebody in his thirties, this one.
# 不好看
It doesn't look good,
# 變黃色的那一種不好
I mean the yellow flowers.
# 哇 挺多的哦
Wa! Quite a lot!
# 今天一下午都摘了好多
We've already picked a lot in just an afternoon today.
# 好 差不多夠了
Alright! I think we should have enough now.
# 這裡有大袋啦
Here's a bag already.
# 裝 裝都裝不 裝都裝不下啦
We can't, we can't take, we can't take anymore.
# 不知道有沒有人摘的到 (註︰不太明白)
I wonder if anyone has picked them.
# 半斤啦
It's a quarter of kilogram here.
# 你看 這個要拿回去慢慢把它摘下來 摘下然後曬乾
Look! We need to bring them home and pick off the flowers one by one. They are then dried under the sun.
# 然後才可以泡茶
Only after that can we use the flowers to make tea.
# 嗯 我們先回去
Um! Let's go back first.
# 走 走走走 沒事 走
C'mon! Let's go, let's go. No worries. Keep going.
# 好像蟲子 回家啦 (註︰不明白甚麼像蟲子)
They look like bugs. Let's go home.
# 我都不怕
I don't even feel scared.
# 剛好攝影小哥的奶奶也在這裡
It just so happens that Mr. Cameraman's grandma is also here.
# 我們一起 一起摘 摘的快一點
Let's do it together, pick together. It's more efficient.
# 把它曬乾 就可以直接泡茶喝啦
Dry them under the sun, then we can use them to make tea right away.
# 摘花
We pick the flowers.
Pick flowers
# 對
Yea!
# 辣手催花 (註︰"deflower"有「破處」的意思，雖然有小孩在，但正是「辣手催花」的意思吧)
We deflower with our cruel hands.
# 是啊
Exactly!
# 它這是把這花丟到盆子裡面去
You know you have to throw the flowers into the pot.
# 小嘟嘟
Little Doo Doo
# 誒
Ey?
# 小嘟嘟 為甚麼你叫小嘟嘟 啊
Little Doo Doo. Why are you called Little Doo Doo, ah?
# 為甚麼
Why?
# 為甚麼你老爸叫你小嘟嘟
Why is your dad calling you Little Doo Doo?
# 因為這個就是我的小名字
Cuz this is my nickname.
# 你的小名字啊
You said it's your nickname?
# 我媽媽叫小嘟嘟
My mom is called Big Doo Doo.
# 哦 這樣啊
Oh! I see!
# 原來是有故事的
I didn't know that. There's a story.
# 是不是
Isn't it?
# 有甚麼故事
What is the story?
# 跟叔叔說一下
C'mon! Let uncle know the story.
# 哦 這樣啊
Oh! I see!
# 這個花已經摘好啦 在樓頂上曬幾天
So all the flowers are picked off. We're gonna dry them under the sun on the rooftop for a few days.
# 曬乾了 就用來泡茶
They can be used to make tea, after being dried.
# 幾天後
A few days later
# 你看 這金銀花曬乾了哦
Look! The honeysuckles have been dried.
# 摘點來泡茶喝一下
Let me take some and make some tea.
# 搞多點花來
I want a bit more flowers.
# 過一下水
Let me drain the water.
# 把蓋子蓋上
Cover it with the lid.
# 要等一下哦 味道還沒出來
We need to wait for a while. The flavour is still not there.
# 現在
Now...
# 等個幾分鐘
It takes a few minutes,
# 味道就出來啦
for the flavour to be released.
# 哇 可以了
Wa! It's alright now!
# 金黃色的液體
The golden yellow liquid,
# 就出來啦
is coming out.
# 嘗一下
Let me have a try.
# 嗯~
Um!
# 很香
It smells really good.
# 香[SIC](應該是「像」)那個花瓣 花的味道
It's like the fragrance of petals, I mean the flowers,
# 金銀花的味道
the honeysuckles.
# 可以喲
Not bad!
# 嘗一下
Have a try!
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.